<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> - Articles</title>
    <description>Blog</description>
    <link>
    </link>
    
      
      <item>
        <title>TDD (Test Driven Development), why bother?</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I came to know about TDD (Test Driven Development), a development methodology in &lt;a href=&quot;http://ajatprabha.in/2017/12/12/sdlc-waterfall-vs-agile/&quot;&gt;Agile Software Craftsmanship&lt;/a&gt;. At first, I was not even sure that how can we write tests to detect bugs in the code, because we write very specific tests that don’t cover every possible use-case. I didn’t understand the purpose of such tests at all. But then digging more into the topic I discovered what is the utility of these tests which I’m going to share in this article.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 17:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2017/12/20/tdd-why-bother</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2017/12/20/tdd-why-bother</guid>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Getting to know SDLC | Waterfall vs Agile Development</title>
        
          <description>&lt;p&gt;I was always curious to know, how a professional business software is developed from start to finish. Unlike what we do during our study of software designing or developing a hobby project, we don’t take the steps involved in making a professional software that seriously! But when you’re out there in the real world you can’t afford to mess things up due to the lack of a streamlined workflow. So while searching for a tested methodology for software development, I came across something called SDLC aka ‘Software Development Life Cycle’. It essentially used to describe the various processes involved in the development of a software viz.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 17:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>
        /2017/12/12/sdlc-waterfall-vs-agile</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/2017/12/12/sdlc-waterfall-vs-agile</guid>
      </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
